<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration of the Queene, mother of the most Christian King Containing the reasons of her departure out of the Low-Countreys; and disadvowing a manifest, set out in her name upon the same argument.</title>
            <title>Declaration da la reyne Mere du Roy tres-Crestien. English</title>
            <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 20 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112376</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847630</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847630</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12680</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12680)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 930:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration of the Queene, mother of the most Christian King Containing the reasons of her departure out of the Low-Countreys; and disadvowing a manifest, set out in her name upon the same argument.</title>
                  <title>Declaration da la reyne Mere du Roy tres-Crestien. English</title>
                  <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Raworth, for Joshua Kirton and Thomas Warren, and are to be sold at their shop, at the signe of the White-horse in Saint Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Declaration da la reyne Mere du Roy tres-Crestien.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With a final imprimatur leaf.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Marie.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Library of Congress.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12680:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12680:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION OF THE QVEENE, Mother of the moſt <hi>CHRISTIAN</hi> KING.</p>
            <p>Containing the reaſons of her depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture out of the <hi>Low-Countreys;</hi> And diſadvowing a <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> ſet out in her Name upon the ſame Argument.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Raworth</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Thomas Warren,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>White-horſe</hi> In Saint <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12680:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12680:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Queene, Mother of the moſt Chriſtian KING, Containing the reaſons of her departure out of the <hi>Low-Countreys,</hi> and diſadvowing a <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> ſet out in her name, upon the ſame Argument.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Erſons of my quality, being placed on the Theatre of the World, and their lives expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to publike view; by how much their Eſtate is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, by ſo much their liberty is the leſſe. For although they are not tyed in Conſcience, to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Actions to any but to God, who is the ſole Judge of their duty; yet, their Honor inforceth them many times to lay open, even their ſecret thoughts to men, who are the Judges of their reputation.</p>
            <p>If then my arrivall in <hi>Flanders</hi> heretofore, hath given ſo much occaſion of diſcourſe to all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome, my departure lately from thence hath cauſed little leſſe throughout all Europe. But as ill Fortune hath as little, wherewithall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12680:3"/>juſt prayſes, as good hath too much to reward flatteries; The miſery of mine in either time hath beene cauſe, that more intereſſed tongues and pennes have beene found to blame me, then charitable to defend me.</p>
            <p>So I underſtand now from all parts, that they endeavour by divers meanes to condemne the deſigne and manner of my departure out of the Low-Countreys, as well by letters, written in ſeverall places, as alſo by memorialls, relations and Gazetts, publiſhed and diſperſed, and by manifeſts, ſet forth even under my owne name; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which one is come to my hand in Print, a piece indeed, which ſeemes to be to my Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; But in effect, tends not but to trouble and imbroyle me on all fides. Briefly, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no Imaginary thing omitted, to give ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Interpretations to my retreat.</p>
            <p>Now, as I have cauſe to feare, that ſo many deviſes may prevaile againſt the ſincerity of my intentions, and inclinations: and to the end, that this pretended Manifeſt, which paſſeth for my owne, may not hereafter be of any force in this nature, eſpecially having been publikely ſeene in my hands, which might ſerve as a tacit Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of it, if I ſhould diſſemble it: e thought it but due to my reputation, and true In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts, to ſet forth this publike Declaration, containing the diſadvowing of that piece, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12680:3"/>ſuch like, if there be any to be found, together with the principall motives, which made me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from the Low-Countreys, the occaſions which made me paſſe into <hi>England,</hi> and the reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions wherein hitherto I remaine, that there may be no cauſe left of ſuch various diſcourſe to my diſadvantage.</p>
            <p>I deſire then that every one may know, That when I took <hi>Flanders</hi> for my refuge, I look't up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that place, but as a neighbour Port, whereto I repaired to avoid the tempeſt, that then diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered me; and not as a Countrey I would have choſen to have remained or ſetled in, my obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation to <hi>France,</hi> being too ſtrict to admit of ſuch a thought.</p>
            <p>I would likewiſe have it knowne, that in all the time I ſojourned in <hi>Flanders,</hi> as well during the Peace, as ſince the rupture betwixt the two Crownes, my principall cares, have tended to my reconciliation with the King my Sonne, and I never concealed this deſire, which even my Sonne in Law the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> did ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to eſteeme both juſt and commendable.</p>
            <p>It is true, that having for the ſpace of ſeaven yeeres in vaine laboured an accommodation, and now diſcovering by adviſe of the wiſer, neither paſſionate, nor intereſſed, and even by reaſon and experience, that after all poſſible care im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12680:4"/>it hath rather beene reconded then ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced; And that the place, wherein I remained ſeemed a perpetuall obſtacle to all encounters, which might lead toward it, as well by reaſon of the breach continued, as alſo for other power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Conſiderations: At laſt, I found it would be moſt agreeable with my affaires, to live (at leaſt for a time) in ſome place free from Suſpition; And the Seaſon being then proper for drinking the Spaw Waters, when I firſt entred into this deliberation, I reſolved to make ſome ſtay in the Country of <hi>Liege,</hi> a place Newtrall, hoping thereby, to finde as well remedy for my indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as expedients for the advancement of my reconciliation.</p>
            <p>This was my cleere Intention without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution concerning my returne into <hi>Flanders;</hi> And to ſpeake the truth, this incertainity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I found my ſelfe, hindred me from communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating the particulars of my deſigne to my Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew the Cardinall Infante; beſides, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments in the warres, held him at ſuch a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from me at the time of my departure, that I could not have opportunity ſo much as to take my leave of him.</p>
            <p>Parting then from <hi>Bruſſells,</hi> I went directly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Liege,</hi> where the expectation of thoſe people was as obſervable as the applauſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I was received in all the Cities of that Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:12680:4"/>And I have reaſon, to acknowledge an oblation to theſe Magiſtrates for the orders, they had given for my reception, whereſoever I was to ſtay. Nevertheleſſe, having before diſpatch'd into <hi>Holland</hi> and other parts, to make proviſion for my ſecurity, during the time I ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Country of <hi>Liege;</hi> beſides, foreſeeing many difficulties in the ſafety of my abode there, I diſcovered that there would have beene yet more in my departure thence, if I ſhould have beene neceſſitated to have left that place, ſo that finding all theſe accidents, as well by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice from ſuch as I had employed abroad, as by the obſervations I made upon the place, where I was, and having yet free paſſage for <hi>Holland,</hi> I thought no time was to be loſt in ſeeking ſome ſafe and quiet habitation which to me was then of moſt importance, conſidering my inconſtant condition. So that for avoyding further hazard, I reſolved preſently to paſſe into <hi>England,</hi> as to the place of moſt ſecurity.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed further in this diſcourſe, I muſt not omit the ſucceſſe, wherewith it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to favour my voyage, which indeed was beyond all that I could deſire. My Couſin, the prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who met me at my very firſt entrance into the Country, received me in the Equipage, I was (which indeed might have made me unknowne) as if my adverſity had ſerved me for ornaments, and as if I had been in as great ſplendor as in my higheſt proſperity. And as for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12680:5"/>the States, they did not entertaine me, as a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of my condition, deſiring paſſage, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a triumphant King, comming to viſite them, and impart his victories to them. And for my Couſin the Princeſſe of Orange, who accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied me through all <hi>Holland,</hi> ſhe lived with me ſo reſpectfully and obliegeingly, and made the Country and her houſes wherein I lodged, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to me, as that I could have almoſt thought them my owne, had not my ill fortune already too much accuſtomed me to know, that they are no more mine. And as to the entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given me by the King of Great Brittaine, my Sonne in Law, all that I can ſay of it, would but derogate from what was publikely ſeen, and my ſelfe muſt acknowledge: By His extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary magnificence at my entrance into <hi>London,</hi> he hath publiſhed the eſteem he had of my Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, by the cheerefulneſſe appearing in his own Countenance, and in that of all his Subjects; he ſhewed how deare my preſence was to him. But above all, I acknowledge the true friendſhip, which I read in his heart, the freenes of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, and the tender affections of the Queen my Daughter, towards me, which have few ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and haue given ſo much eaſe to my preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing afflictions, that it could not have been more, if God had ſent an angel from heaven to comfort me. Inſomuch, that I could not have had in all my voyage other occaſion then of joy, if thoſe things, which were prepared for my delight had
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12680:5"/>not likewiſe beene Subjects of my Sorrow: In that they made me thinke, that the late King, my lord, appeared yet living in my perſon in ſtrange Countrys, but in effect his very memory ſeemed dead for my ſake in his owne Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now to returne to my diſcourſe; I muſt ſay, that having runne over all that hath paſt in this my retreat from <hi>Flanders,</hi> I cannot thinke, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny can charge me with neglect of my reputation for my diligence in the good of my affaires, nor that it will be hard to perſwade ſuch, as will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently judge thereof, that in this Retreat I have done any thing, either in Circumſtances or Conſequences, more, then all the time I ſojour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Low-Countries, which may be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to gratitude: And I adde, that I had done nothing unſeemly, if, when I had left the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of <hi>Spain,</hi> I had remained in <hi>Holland,</hi> though it be an Enemies Country; becauſe in this Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I had not ſought <hi>Holland,</hi> as an Enemy to <hi>Spaine,</hi> but as an Allie and Confederate with <hi>France.</hi> And this quality of <hi>Holland,</hi> which was then advantagious to me, was not hurtfull to <hi>Spaine,</hi> in profiting me, So that remaining in <hi>Holland,</hi> I ſhould not have prejudiced <hi>Spaine,</hi> in doing my ſelfe good.</p>
            <p>And as for the bruites ſpread abroad, that I went into <hi>Holland</hi> to doe ill offices to <hi>Spaine,</hi> and that ſome of my people by order from me, had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12680:6"/>given up to my Couſin the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> the Mappe of ſundry places of the Low-Countries; It is a rumour ſo ridiculous, that it deſerves no anſwer but of ſcorne. Surely it had been much to my credit, by this example to have demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to my Couſin the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived me ſo courteouſly, how well I uſed my hoſts when I was gone from them, and beſides, in giving him a good impreſſion of my integrity, I had alſo made him know that I had a better of his providence, judging it ſuch, as that he had not care enough to provide himſelfe of a Platt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme of all the places of the Low-Countries. Truly this would have paſſed for a faire Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment at my arrivall.</p>
            <p>And this rumor is not more contemptible then another quite contrary is falſe, ſavoring of a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious Invention, That I ſhould go into <hi>Holland</hi> to treat of the Truce, or to practiſe againſt that State, and againſt my Couſin the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> under the pretence of hoſpitality.</p>
            <p>But time having made appear even to the moſt ſimple, that theſe rumours were altogether falſe, and reaſon having made the wiſeſt apprehend, that they had no reſemblance of truth: I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon that which is of more weight, and for Juſtification of all my deſignes, declare ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, what were the motives of my reſolution, in regard both of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> whilſt I remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12680:6"/>in the Low-Countreys, and, why I retired from thence.</p>
            <p>All the time I paſſed in <hi>Flanders,</hi> I kept this Temper, that my affections, as well as my beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, were al waies Neutrall in reſpect of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique affaires betweene <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine.</hi> The aſſiſtance which I received from <hi>Spaine</hi> on one ſide, and the Obligations, which I had to <hi>France</hi> on the other ſide, obliged me to carry my ſelfe in that Manner. And to ſpeake cleerely, I ſhould have held it as unjuſt, whileſt I remained in the Dominions of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and lived at their expence, to take part with <hi>France,</hi> to the prejudice of <hi>Spain,</hi> as contrary to my owne inclination to have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken part with <hi>Spaine</hi> to the prejudice of <hi>France.</hi> And howſoever that pretended Manifeſt ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating the complaints, which it makes under my name of <hi>Spaine,</hi> doth artificially inſinuate, that I have borne much affection to the good of their affaires, which is but a hidden venome, to perplex me on the part of <hi>France,</hi> The truth is, that <hi>Spain</hi> in that point hath no more obligation to me then that I have ever paſſionately longed for that Union and Concord between thoſe two Crowns, whereof in former times I had laid the foundations by a double Alliance. And that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides I have alwayes endeavoured ſince the rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to contribute all I was able to the reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of Peace.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:12680:7"/>
            <p>God forbid, I ſhould deſire to pay the new obligations, I have to <hi>Spaine,</hi> to the prejudice of thoſe ancient bonds, which I have contracted with <hi>France,</hi> it is to that I have vowed my firſt affections, And it is that, which ſhall for ever keepe them with the aſhes of my deceaſed Lord.</p>
            <p>But God forbid likewiſe, that for any advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage I might have from <hi>France,</hi> it ſhould ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into my thoughts, to diſadvow the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions I have to <hi>Spaine.</hi> I know too well, that it is the utmoſt degree of ingratitude to denie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits received; I am ſo farre from that, that I will alwayes proclaime them with advantage. And I confeſſe it troubles me that I have no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes to acquit my ſelfe then on all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (as on this) to acknowledge the ſubſiſtence, which the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> my Sonne in Law gave me ſeven yeers together, and the proofs of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall love, which I received from the Queen my Daughter, the care which my late ſiſter the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanta had of my perſon: who beſides did no leſſe inſtruct me with her vertues, then comfort me with her good offices: And laſtly the great cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie and good will of my Nephew the Cardinal Infante: All which, are effects which I referre principally to the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> my Sonne in Law, to whoſe intentions my Nephew and my deceaſed Siſter, the Infanta, have but joyned their naturall inclinations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12680:7"/>
            <p>Moreover I am farre from weakening theſe publike teſtimonies (which I deſire to confirme in all places) by making complaint againſt any of his Officers, and herein I am injured by the Authors of that pretended <hi>Manifest,</hi> in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing falſe ones to the view of the world, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my name; On the contrary it imports me, that it be knowne (as it is true) that in caſe there had been any diſreſpect of me through the fault of any Officers in <hi>Flanders</hi> (which yet would have been contrary to the orders of the King of <hi>Spaine</hi> my Sonne in Law) the good entertainment I received from the Maſter would in my opinion have covered the errour of the Servants, And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though peradventure it would not have taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way my reſſentiment of it, yet diſcretion would have taught me to have concealed it.</p>
            <p>Neither ſhall it ever be ſayd, that any ſuch thing falls from me, But rather expreſſions of the entire ſatisfaction I received from the King of <hi>Spain</hi> my Sonne in Law, And at my departure from the Hague, I diſpatched an expreſſe to my Nephew the Cardinall Infante, to teſtifie to him my Acknowledgements and to let him under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my intention of comming out of the Low-Countries: which is the ſame wherein this day I perſiſt, and which I will cleerely expreſſe to conclude this Declaration.</p>
            <p>My end neither was nor is in all theſe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
<pb facs="tcp:12680:8"/>any other then my reconciliation with the King my Son: To the effecting of which, thoſe meanes, which would ſeeme hard and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to perſons of my quality; ſhall be pleaſant and eaſie to me. Nor doe I accompt it of the number of thoſe painefull means, to affect thoſe whom he honors with his principall truſt: I will do that willingly though they give me no cauſe: and am reſolved to omit nothing (no not that which I ſhall know to be in vaine) to gaine the friendſhip of the King my Sonne.</p>
            <p>It would be a happines precious to me, yet due by ſo many juſt Titles that I hold my ſelfe as blameles for the pretending to it, as innocent of the leaſt ambition thereby to partake of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Nor ſhould I pardon my ſelfe if I had any temptation of that nature, and withall, if I held not that authority as unuſefull for my par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular happines, as I eſteem the love of the King my Sonne, neceſſary to my preſent contentment.</p>
            <p>And it will be eaſie to beleeve, that I am of this opinion, if the preſent may be judged by what is paſt, and to that end it may be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red how I behaved my ſelfe during my regency, wherein I made uſe of it, and with what Spirit I governed, when through my misfortune and that of <hi>France,</hi> in looſing the late King my Lord, I was ingaged to imploy my care and diligence, to uphold the publique affaires, which were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12680:8"/>then in eminent danger: And when the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Vote and conſent of the ſtates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome had committed to my care, the fortune of the State, I think I ſo forgot my own, that even Slander and my enemies together, never drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to lay to my charge, that I had any thought of making Advantage of that Authority: Nor that Ambition or Intereſt had upon any occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Vote in my private Councells. As for the former, it cannot be doubted, ſince it is cleere, that I never ſought in all my Regency other glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, then to leave the Kingdome as quiet and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing under the government of a woman (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all the troubles, that then come upon it) as one of the greateſt Kings of the world ſaw it at his death, after twelve yeeres of ſetled peace. And as for Intereſt, I dare boldly ſay, without offence to modeſty (and <hi>France</hi> cannot without ingratitude deny it) that I ſo ordered the Treaſure of my Son, that in preſerving it, I had care of it, as of my owne; but in expending it, I conſidered it as the goods of another. So that at the end of my labours, there is nothing left me, but the quality of a Mother, which God himſelfe cannot take from me.</p>
            <p>Theſe actions, whereof the publique monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments themſelves will be for ever witneſſes, are the only Trophees, which I have erected to my Memory. Theſe Actions, I ſay, are the only Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadells, which I have rais'd to my defence and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12680:9"/>have built in the heart of the King my Sonne, in that of the French, and in my owne Conſcience. But certainly not to deceive my ſelfe, it is upon this laſt foundation, whereon I ſettle my princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall hopes, and in all accidents, my moſt ſolide ſatisfaction. And laſtly, although it ſhould hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by the ſecret reaſons of Gods Providence, that the reſt of my days ſhould paſſe in diſgrace, and though I ſhould never have before my death the comfort of ſeeing the King my Sonne, yet I will not leave to give him, abſent, as now I doe, my continuall bleſſings. And I will finiſh my life, as I now end this Declaration; Beſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching God that theſe my bleſſings may be as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall to him, as if I had been ever favourably treated.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Signed</hi> Marie.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>and underneath is written,
</closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <hi>This Declaration hath beene read publikely before the whole Court of the Queen, in preſence of her Majeſtie. And after it was Signed with her own hand and by her commandement, the Originall remaines in the hand of the Vicount.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>FABRONI.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
            <pb facs="tcp:12680:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
